Preliminary Guide to the Walter Gordy Papers, 1935 - 1986 UA.29.02.0034
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Walter Gordy papers
1935 - 1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gordy, Walter, 1909-1985
UA.29.02.0034
37.5 Linear Feet
Walter Gordy (1909-1985) was a James B. Duke Professor of Physics at Duke University. In his over thirty year career at Duke, he founded and directed the Duke Microwave Laboratory, and researched and published extensively. The Walter Gordy Papers include correspondence, bibliographies, vita, articles, speeches, notebooks, teaching materials, illustrations, photographs, and graphs of experimental results. Major subjects include microwave spectroscopy, microwave radar, the Duke Microwave Laboratory, Army research Office, Durham (ARO-D), and the Duke Department of Physics. English.
29,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Walter Gordy Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1989 (A89-0062, A89-99) and a transfer in 1993 (A93-36, A93-40) and 2007 (UA2007-0023).
Biographical Note
Walter Gordy was born on April 20, 1909 in Newton County Mississippi. After receiving a B.A. from Mississippi College in 1932, he received his M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill in 1932 and 1935, respectively. From 1935 to 1941, Gordy served as a professor of physics at Mary Hardin-Baylor College in Texas. He then worked at Cal Tech with Linus Pauling and later in the Radiation Kabiratirt at MIT.
In 1946, Gordy joined the faculty of the Duke University Department of Physics. During his tenure, he contributed to the development of microwave radar and microwave spectroscopy through his work in the Duke Microwave Laboratory, which he founded and headed. He published many articles and four books, and was a member of numerous professional organizations. In 1958, Gordy was named a James B. Duke Professor. Gordy died in Durham on October 6, 1985. He was survived by his wife of fifty years, Vida.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, bibliographies, vita, articles, speeches, notebooks, teaching materials, illustrations, photographs, and graphs of experimental results. The materials date from approximately 1935 to 1986. Gordy's professional career, particularly his work at Duke, is well represented. Much of the material stems from his research in the Duke Microwave Laboratory. The correspondence in the collection is mainly professional. A few materials, such as trip souvenirs, represent Gordy's personal life.
Related Material
Department of Physics records
Duke University Archives
Microwaves -- Research; Microwave spectroscopy; Physics -- Research; Physics -- Experiments -- Methodology; Physics -- Study and teaching; Slides (photographs); Photographs; Negatives (photographic); Duke University. Department of Physics; Gordy, Walter, 1909-1985; Gordy, Walter, 1909-1985
- Accession Number A89-62
  Arrangement note
  The Gordy papers are only preliminarily processed. The lists of materials within each box represent major subjects, but they are not folder lists.
  - Reprints on Microwaves (Box 1)
  - Clippings on Gordy (Box 1)
  - Memorial Service Materials (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Professional (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Congratulatory (Box 1)
  - Campus Club Materials (Mrs. Gordy) (Box 1)
  - Gordy's c.v. (Box 1)
  - Photographs - Physics Department faculty, Gordys in USSR (Box 1)
  - List of Microwave Laboratory Ph.D.s (Box 1)
  - Student Ph.D. Thesis (Box 1)
  - Reprints and Journals (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - A-W (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - W-Z (Box 2)
  - Exchange Visit (Correspondence), 1974 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - A-W (Box 2)
  - Correspondence - W (Box 3)
  - High School Validictory speech (Box 3)
  - Misc. Professional Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Reprints (Box 3)
  - List of Students (Box 3)
  - Microwave Directory (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Professional and University (Box 3)
  - Speech notes (Box 3)
  - Conference Materials (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - re: prizes won by Gordy (Box 3)
  - Notebook on experiments (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - Conferences (Box 3)
  - Conference Materials (Box 3)
  - Gordy's Ph.D. Thesis and Abstract (Box 3)
  - List of Published Papers by the Duke Microwave Laboratory (Box 3)
  - Biographical Material (Box 3)
  - Evaluation of Physics Department (Box 3)
  - Information on Duke Microwavers, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence - University of Florida and University of Texas (Box 3)
  - Notecards listing Gordy publications (Box 4)
  - Research - Charts and Graphs (Box 4)
  - Conference materials (Box 4)
  - Reprints (Box 4)
  - Duke University Distinguished Professor Award program and photographs (Box 4)
  - UNC Distinguished Alumni photograph (Box 4)
  - Popular Lectures and Articles (Box 4)
  - Report on Exchange Visit to Yugoslavia (Box 4)
  - Papers by Gordy (Box 4)
  - Notes for Acceptance Speech for N.C. Award for Science (Box 4)
  - Speeches by Gordy (including notes) (Box 4)
  - Millimeter and Submillimeter Wave Developments at Duke University (Box 5)
  - Information on Awards Received by Gordy (Box 5)
  - Nomination of Walter Gordy for the North Carolina Award in Science (Box 5)
  - Duke Microwavers Information (Box 5)
  - Notebooks from courses and research, [Approx. 20] (Box 5)
  - Notebook (Box 6)
  - Research notes and charts (Box 6)
  - Correspondence - re: submissions for publication (Box 6)
  - Duke Microwave Laboratory personnel information - RESTRICTED (Box 6)
  - Sketches (Box 6)
  - Reprints (Box 6)
  - Photographs of physicists and equipment (Box 6)
  - Clippings (Box 6)
  - Information on conference held in honor of Gordy (Box 6)
  - Conference materials (Box 6)
  - Roster of Physics Ph.D.s from Duke (Box 6)
  - Unbound copy of Microwave Spectroscopy (Box 6)
  - Correspondence - re: submissions for publication (Box 6)
  - Biographical Information (Box 6)
  - Student Papers - RESTRICTED (Box 7)
  - Clippings (Box 7)
  - Maps and information about Harvard and MIT (Box 7)
  - Touraide (driving map) (Box 7)
  - Trip Souvenirs (placemats, guide books, etc.) (Box 7)
  - Photographs of research results (Box 7)
  - Negatives of research results (Box 7)
  - Glass and plastic slides (Box 7)
  - Technical illustrations (Box 7)
- Accession Number A89-99
  - Papers relating to the nomination of Dr. Gordy for the North Carolina Award in Science, 1979 (Box 7)
- Accession Number A93-40
  - Microwave Spectroscopy of Biological Substances, Pts. I and II [paper written by Gordy and others] (Box 7)
  - Duke Microwave Laboratory - Published Papers, 1946-1978 (Box 7)
  - Duke Microwave Laboratory - Personnel Rosters, 1946-1978 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 7)
- Oversized Materials [from Accession Number A89-62]
  - Certificates of Life Membership in the UNC General Alumni Association for the Gordys (Box 8)
  - Posters and announcements on talks by Gordy (Box 8)
  - Research charts and graphs (Box 8)
- Accession Number UA2007-0023
  - Correspondence I (1961-1980), A-H (Box 9)
  - Correspondence I (1961-1980), H-N (Box 10)
  - Correspondence I (1961-1980), O-S (Box 11)
  - Correspondence I (1961-1980), S-Z (Box 12)
  - Correspondence II (1953-1960), A-F (Box 13)
  - Correspondence II (1953-1960), G-P (Box 14)
  - Correspondence II (1953-1960), P-Z (Box 15)
  - Air Force contract ledgers (Box 16)
    - 1947-1952 (Box 16)
    - 1952-1960 (Box 16)
    - 1960-1967 (Box 16)
  - Files associated with the Air Force contract 1946-1953 (reports, etc, not checked for identity with published papers.) (Box 16)
  - Meeting correspondence, associated manuscripts (Box 17)
  - Correspondence associated with other manuscripts (Box 17)
  - APS, NAS, IUPAC correspondence (Box 17)
  - Correspondence associated with Army Research Office, Durham (AROD) (Box 18)
  - Correspondence with M. Katayama (Box 18)
  - Correspondence with Duke University Planning Commission (Box 18)
  - "Recent Correspondence" 1963-1966 (Box 18)
  - Mixed correspondence and papers, 1954-1974 (Box 18)
  - Mixed paper (Box 19)
  - Teaching materials (Box 19)
  - Duke development, 1958 (Box 19)
  - Mixed papers (note letter to Tribble) (Box 19)
  - AROD contract accounting, 1969-1972 (Box 19)
  - Air Force contract, 1955-1971 (Box 19)
  - Air Force contract (con't) (Box 20)
    - Correspondence (Box 20)
    - Proposals (Box 20)
    - Reports (Box 20)
  - Office of Ordinance Research (OOR) contract (Box 20)
  - "Miscellaneous" correspondence, 1953-1960 (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1952-1966 (Box 21)
  - Air Force, payroll 1953-1960 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1946-1951 (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1946-1951, continued (Box 22)
  - Previously classified technical reports (Box 22)
  - Binder and documents concerning Gordy's employment (1935-1941): Baylor College, Cal Tech, Linus Pauling etc. (Box 23)
  - ESR spectra (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1950s (Box 23)
  - Christmas and private correspondence with former student, post-docs, and colleagues (Box 24)
  - Addressbook (Box 24)
  - Notes for talks at several 'Microwave dinner(s)' at APS meetings, Washington, D.C., circa 1964-1968 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, A-M, 1951-1961 (Box 24)
  - AROD grant-related correspondence, 1951; 1962-1970 (Box 25)
  - Binders with grant accounting, 1962-1970 (Box 25)
  - Items retained from invoice files, 1946-1961 (Box 25)